Documenting Lesbian Lives Oral History Project oral histories SSC.MS.00661
Sophia Smith Collection
- Documenting Lesbian Lives, 2019 March-April; 2019-S-0016; Anderson, Kelly; 0.625 linear feet (1 Letter document box, 1 half letter document box); 1800 Gigabytes (70 digital files)
  - Ruth "Reg" Grauert interviewed by Sofia Engelman with Molly Hess, 2019 March 15; 2019-S-0016; Grauert, Ruth "Reg"; Engleman, Sofia; Hess, Molly; 1 oral histories (Transcript and video)
    In this interview, Grauert reflects on her experience and understanding of significant American events, including the Great Depression, the presidential election of 1932, World War II, and the Lincoln, Kennedy, and Trump Administrations. She also discusses her involvement in the rise of modern dance and her experience touring with the Nikolais company for decades, as well as the summer camp, Bearnstow, which she founded with her partner Francis. Grauert reflects on issues of race, class, gender, disability, and sexuality in relation to these subjects.
    Ruth "Reg" Grauert was born on March 24, 1919 in Jersey City. She received a BA from Ursinus College in 1939 and an MA from Columbia University in 1941. Reg studied dance with the likes of Martha Graham, Hanya Holma, and Charles Weidman during and after graduate school. After graduate school, she taught junior high and high school in Connecticut and New York City. In New York City, after World War II, she began assisting and working as a lighting designer and stage manager for the well-known modern dance choreographer Alwin Nikolais. Reg also taught dance to children at the esteemed Henry St. Playhouse for decades while living in New York.
    In 1945, Reg and her partner Francis Reid, who were together until Francis' death, decided they wanted to open a summer camp in rural Maine. They ultimately purchased an abandoned property on Parker Pond in Mt. Vernon, Maine, a town popular for summer camps. They repaired the property themselves and prepared to make a camp that was "ethical. It was to be interracial, interreligious, and co-ed, and offer the arts and non-competitive sports." Reg continues to serve as the director of Bearnstow today which is open each summer holding a day camp and summer dance workshops for adults. During the year she claims to be a "shut-in" in Jersey City.
    - Video interview of Ruth "Reg" Grauert, 2019-S-0016
    - Transcript of interview of Ruth "Reg" Grauert, 2019 March 15; 2019-S-0016 (Box 1)
  - Jack Halberstam interviewed by Sky Karp, 2019 March 20; 2019-S-0016; Halberstam, Jack; Karp, Sky; 1 oral histories (Transcript and video)
    In this interview, Halberstam reflects on his childhood in Nottingham, coming into the queer community in the Bay Area and Minneapolis, and his experience as a professor.
    Halberstam shares his insightful views on aging as a queer person, building relationships with younger generations and his experience of embodiment over his lifetime. Halberstam's interview is a fantastic window into the experiences and histories of transmasculine and butch individuals coming into their identities in the eighties and nineties.
    Jack Halberstam (b. 1961) is a native of Nottingham, in the UK. He received his BA from UC Berkeley in 1985 and his PhD from University of Minnesota in 1991, both in English. He was an Associate Professor in Literature at the University of California at San Diego and a Professor of American Studies and Ethnicity, Gender Studies, and Comparative Literature at the University of Southern California, before his appointment as professor of English and Comparative Literature at Columbia University in 2017. Halberstam is the author of six books: Skin Shows: Gothic Horror and the Technology of Monsters (1995), Female Masculinity (1998), In a Queer Time and Place (2005), The Queer Art of Failure, Gaga Feminism: Sex, Gender, and the End of Normal (2011), and Trans* (2018).
    Halberstam has been involved in the queer community in the Bay Area, Minneapolis and New York City. He currently lives in Brooklyn with his partner, Macarena Gomez-Barris and her two children.
    - Video interview of Jack Halberstam, 2019-S-0016
    - Transcript of interview of Jack Halberstam, 2019 March 20; 2019-S-0016 (Box 1)
  - Caroline McDaniel interviewed by Franchesca Therpenier, 2019 March 12; 2019-S-0016; McDaniel, Caroline; Therpenier, Franchesca; 1 oral histories (Transcript and video)
    In this interview, McDaniel reflects on her childhood, what it was like growing up in Floria, and the pain of loss within the family. She discusses in great detail what Smith College was like in the mid-1980s and the lesbian culture that existed when she was a student. McDaniel tells stories of being a woman chef in a culture of toxic masculinity in professional kitchens. Having spent much of her life in New York, she describes the AIDS epidemic in the '80s and '90s, the aftermath of 9/11, and the gentrification of the city. She speaks about the pitfalls of "tolerance" and "acceptance," emphasizing the need for society to be open towards individuals and their identities.
    Caroline McDaniel (b. 1963) was born and raised in Miami, Florida. Her father, John McDaniel, was a pilot, which allowed her to travel a lot in her early life. Her older brother, Doug McDaniel, passed away from Leukemia when she was a child, creating distance between her and her father. Caroline has a very close relationship with her mother, Athena, and her grandmother, Thelxiope.
    Caroline McDaniel came to Northampton, Massachussetts, in 1981 to attend Smith College, graduating in '85 with a degree in Sociology. Afterwards, she attended cooking school in Paris and had tense interactions with her male peers. She opened up a patisserie in Northampton in 1987, which closed over a year later due to a stagnant economy. She lived in New York City during most of the 1990s and had a long-term relationship and domestic partnership with Margaret Noble. Caroline moved back to Northampton in 2012 to open ConVino Wine Bar and has been living here ever since.
    - Video interview of Caroline McDaniel, 2019-S-0016
    - Transcript of interview of Caroline McDaniel, 2019 March 12; 2019-S-0016 (Box 1)
  - Pam Parmakian interviewed by Olivia Laursen, 2019 March 23; 2019-S-0016; Parmakian, Pam; Laursen, Olivia; 1 oral histories (Transcript and video)
    In this interview, Parmakian reflects on her life history. This includes her childhood, coming out, the social life in Provincetown, changes to community in Provincetown as a resuly of gentrification, trauma, complicated family relationships, love and marriage, and queer family-making. Through her humor, vulnerability, and candid storytelling, Parmakian provides insight into lesbian life in a gay mecca and a window into the complex emotional lives of gay women.
    Pam Parmakian (b. 1959) is originally from Wethersfield, CT. She was one of four children, and grew up working in her family's successful catering business. She came out around age 18 and first visited Provincetown, MA at age 20 - then stayed there year-round for the next 27 years. She was an active part of the vibrant social community and party scene there, including during the HIV/AIDS crisis. She worked to develop a lesbian community in Provincetown by organizing benefit events, parties, and Women's Week, as well as by managing a large women's guesthouse (Gabriel's) and, later, a popular women's nightclub (the Vixen). As gentrification accelerated in Provincetown, Parmakian began working in affordable housing and the local government as a Selectperson. Through her work in affordable housing, she met her wife Elizabeth Bridgewater in 2006, and they were married in 2009. Together, they eventually left the Cape to live full-time in western Massachussetts. Though the couple do not have children of their own, their relationship with Parmakian's grand-niece is very special and important. She currently works in Amherst, MA for the Amherst House Authority and lives with her wife and their dog in Greenfield, MA.
    - Video interview of Pam Parmakian, 2019-S-0016
    - Transcript of interview of Pam Parmakian, 2019 March 23; 2019-S-0016 (Box 1)
  - Beaujan Sneed interviewed by Lauren Ramos, 2019 March 11; 2019-S-0016; Sneed, Beaujan; Ramos, Lauren; 1 oral histories (Transcript and video)
    In this oral history, Sneed explains her coming out process and her experience with on-and offline support groups that helped her through it. She then explains the difficulties she faced when attempting to divorce her husband and obtain custody of her two young children after coming out as a lesbian, noting the help she received from the National Center for Lesbian Rights throughout her custody battle. Sneed describes her work with Gyrlgroove, a women's production company, and continued involvement with organizations such as the Lesbian Social Group of Knoxville, which she now leads. She discusses several of the relationships she has been in and explains how she came to identifiy with different labels for her sexual orientation (including "lesbian," "bisexual," "demisexual," "hot mess," and "woman who loves women").
    Sneed touches on connections and tensions between the transgender and lesbian communities in Knoxville as well as the differences she has noticed between the older and younger generations in the community. Sneed talks about her experience with her pansexual daughter and with LGBTQ youth that she has taken under her wing, demonstrating the importance of connection and friendship for LGBTQ people and emphasizing the need to avoid isolation.
    Throughout this oral history, Sneed touches on LGBTQ identity and community formation, connection and tensions in lesbian spaces, online activism, relationships, LGBTQ family, and intergenerational connection between LGBTQ people. This oral history is an excellent example of the work of LGBTQ activists in the South, particularly regarding ongoing changes in activist work that have come with the rise of the digital age.
    Beaujan Sneed (b. 1968) grew up in Cleveland, Tennessee. After high school, she married a man and travelled with the military before settling down in Knoxville, Tennessee, in 1999. There, she found community with the Lesbian Social Group of Knoxville before coming out and later divorcing her husband. After a two-year custody battle, with assistance from the National Center for Lesbian Rights, she gained joint custody of her two children and set a precedent for custody agreements of other lesbian mothers in Knoxville. Sneed became deeply engaged with activism in her area, including working for Gyrlgroove and leading the Lesbian Social Group of Knoxville, Southern Rainbows TN, and Women Keeping It Real TN.She also collaborates with other organizations in her community, such as the Voices for Trans Youth Campaign, Knoxville Pride, and CONTACT Care Line, among many others. Sneed currently lives in Knoxville, TN, where she continues to advocate for change.
    - Video interview of Beaujan Sneed, 2019-S-0016
    - Transcript of interview of Beaujan Sneed, 2019 March 11; 2019-S-0016 (Box 1)
  - Anita Stuart interviewed by Zoe Nadig, 2019 March 16; 2019-S-0016; Stuart, Anita; Nadig, Zoe; 1 oral histories (Transcript and video)
    In this interview, Stuart reflects on her life, touching on principle themes of music, love and family, as well as life in Berkshire Country, MA, where she has lived on and off for sixty years. She talks about the ease of coming out in middle age and her relationship with her wife.
    Anita Stuart (b. 1950) was born in Brooklyn, NY, but considers her true home Berkshire Country in Western Massachussetts where she has lived on and off since she was a child. She attended UMass Amherst for one year before transferring to Boston University to get her Bachelor of Fine Arts in Music Performance, focusing on the organ. She later got her Teachers Certification from Westfield State University and from 1991 to 2008 taught music at the Lenox Public Schools. Since 1992 she has served as choir director and organist at Trinity Episcopal Church in Lenox. She has two daughters with her ex-husband and currently lives with her wife, Gail Street, in Lenox, Massachussetts.
    - Video interview of Anita Stuart, 2019-S-0016
    - Transcript of interview of Anita Stuart, 2019 March 16; 2019-S-0016 (Box 1)
  - Lenora Trussell interviewed by Julia Cornick, 2019 March 23; 2019-S-0016; Trussell, Lenora; Cornick, Julia; 1 oral histories (Transcript and video)
    In this interview, Trussell reflects on her childhood and specifically on her relationships with her siblings. She wrestles with themes of truth and memory, as many of her family members (both in her family of origin as a child and her partner later in life) lied to her. She recounts her experience as a young lesbian in Alabama and D.C. during the 1960s-1980s, such as being in a gay bar during a raid and her experience with using a gay sperm donor to conceive her son during the early days of the AIDS crisis. Trussell discusses the abuse she has experienced throughout her life, and how she has come to view abuse and healing, both in her own life and in the world as a whole.
    There is no audiovisual component offor this interview, only a transcript.
    Lenora Trussell (b. 1948) began her life in Kane, Pennsylvania, but moved around numerous times as a child, and counts 17 different places that she lived with her family before she went away to college at the age of 16. She attended Florence State University (now known as the University of North Alabama) and graduated with a Bachelor of Arts in Zoology.
    After graduating college, Trussell held many different jobs, mostly in the healthcare field, and got her nusring degree from Georgia State University. Her jobs have included processing pap smears in a hospital, working at a suicide prevention hotline, giving massages, owning a gay bed and breakfast, and being a hospice nurse (which she described as her "favorite"). She gave birth to her son when she was in her mid-thirties through a sperm donor, and they currently live in Greenfield, MA.
    - Transcript of interview of Lenora Trussell, 2019 March 23; 2019-S-0016 (Box 2)
  - Lise Weil interviewed by Amanda Carberry, 2019 March 20; 2019-S-0016; Weil, Lise; Carberry, Amanda; 1 oral histories (Transcript and video)
    In this interview, Lise Weil reflects on her early fascination with learning and knowledge (and the women who provided that knowledge), her entrance into the lesbian feminist scene, her relationship to labels of identity, her connection to music as an accompaniment to her life and lesbian identity, her relationships, her perception of conflict within the lesbian community, and the evolution of her understanding of love and desire. Weil shares nostalgic observations about the loss of lesbian spaces and considers topics such as the relationship of lesbians to outsider-hood and alienation, marriage and existing outside of a traditional family structure, visions for the future, and the nature of political activity. Weil's interview provides an invigorating and thought-provoking window into the lesbian feminist movement of the 1970s and 1980s and offers highly-attuned perceptions regarding the groundbreaking place the movement occupied in history.
    Lise Weil is a Chicago-born writer, editor and translator who has called Montreal her home since 1990. She attended Cornell University as an undergraduate and received both her MA and Phd from Brown University in 1977 and 1987, respectively. She joined the faculty of Goddard College in Vermont in 1993 and remains a faculty member in the Goddard Graduate Institute, where she prides herself in being a "recovering academic" engaged in forging alternative, politicized learning spaces. She was the founder and editor of the U.S. feminist review Trivia: A Journal of Ideas and of its online offshoot, Trivia: Voices of Feminism, an award-winning radical feminist literary and political magazine. She is currently the founder and editor of Dark Matter: Women Witnessing, and Earth-centered publication dedicated to reflection on the relationship of the human to the non-human world in an age of ecological collapse.
    Lise Weil's engagement with the lesbian feminist movement began with her coming out in 1976. Her time at the Women's Writer's Center in New York from 1978 to 1980 was integral to cultivating her writing and her engagement with major feminist thinkers of the time. During the 1980s, she lived in Western Massachussetts, residing for a time in the house of radical feminist philosopher Mary Daly. There, she participated in a radical women's study group, from which the foundational ideas for Trivia and its publication emerged, and enjoyed a deep connection to nature. She moved to Montreal in 1990, a time when it was home to a vibrant lesbian culture. It is a city she still loves for its multiculturalism, multilingualism, and laissez-faire nature.
    Lise Weil's memoir, In Search of Pure Lust, appeared in June 2018 with She Writes Press in the U.S. and Inanna Press in Canada. The book served as the basis of a talk given at Smith College on March 20, 2019, directly following this interview. Lise continues to live in Montreal, and enjoys hosting and facilitating women's writing retreats on a regular basis. She is a Sagittarius with an Aquarius moon.
    - Video interview of Lise Weil, 2019-S-0016
    - Transcript of interview of Lise Weil, 2019 March 20; 2019-S-0016 (Box 2)
  - Karla Westphal interviewed by Clara Rosenberg, 2019 March 10; 2019-S-0016; Westphal, Karla; Rosenberg, Clara; 1 linear feet (Transcript and video)
    In this oral history, Westphal discusses growing up in a religious household and eventually losing her faith. She talks about discovering her bisexuality during college and her subsequent involvement in various LGBT groups, as well as current involvement with the Golden State Squares, a gay square dancing group. She reflects on a couple of past romantic relationships, and discusses the path she took that led her to be a mathematics professor. She also describes the process of suing the community college she works at over prayer at public events.
    Karla Westphal (b. 1971) grew up in Michigan and Long Island, New York. She received a Bachelor's degree from Yale in theater and philosophy, and a Master's degree from Loyola University Chicago in mathematics. She came out as bisexual in her first year of college, and has varying degrees of involvement with the LGBT community since then. She currently works as a mathematics professor at a community college, and lives in Orange County, California.
    - Video interview of Karla Westphal, 2019-S-0016
    - Transcript of interview of Karla Westphal, 2019 March 10; 2019-S-0016 (Box 2)
  - Stacey Zaremba interviewed by Julia Fraivillig, 2019 March 13; 2019-S-0016; Zaremba, Stacey; Fraivillig, Julia; 1 oral histories (Transcript and video)
    In this interview, Zaremba looks back on her family life, her professional studies, and her current impact on students who are LGBT and students who are pursuing women's issues. Zaremba reflects on family relationships and how coming into her identity as a woman who loves women has been shaped by them.
    Stacey Zaremba (b. 1960) was born in Brooklyn, New York. She attended school there, eventually earning her PhD in Psychology from Fordham University. She later moved to Pennsylvania when she joined the faculty of Moravian College in 1989.
    There, Zaremba is very involved with women's issues. She is the director of the Women's Studies department, having established when she first arrived. Zaremba's experimental psychology has focused on the psychology of gender, and she introduces those ideas into research of feminist pedagogy.
    Zaremba has been involved in many organizations over her career including the YWCA in Bethlehem and multiple chapters of the American Association of University Women.
    - Video interview of Stacey Zaremba, 2019-S-0016
    - Transcript of interview of Stacey Zaremba, 2019 March 13; 2019-S-0016 (Box 2)
  - Kathleen Zeamer interviewed by Ruby Lowery, 2019 March 31; 2019-S-0016; Zeamer, Kathleen; Lowery, Ruby; 1 oral histories (Transcript and video)
    In this interview, Zeamer describes her experience growing up in a working-class family in Columbia, PA. She describes her passion for tennis growing up and how through sports she was able to find community - both in high school and college. Zeamer discusses her participation in the lesbian-feminist movement while living in Southeastern Virginia: revolving around music festivals, workshops, readings, and Take Back the Night marches. She also dicusses her traveling book business, New Country Books. She reflects on the differences in her communities living in the South versus Western Massachussetts, and how that affected the ways women organized and created networks. Through this oral history. Zeamer examines the unique experiences that come with aging and being lesbian, while considering the ways lesbian spaces have disappeared or changed over time.
    Kathleen Zeamer (b. 1955) was born and raised in Columbia, PA to a working-class family. She attended East Stroundsburg State College and received her undergraduate degree in Interdisciplinary Environmental Studies in 1976. After graduating, she moved to Maryland where she began her career with the U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service that spanned for over thirty years at several stations.
    While living in Southeastern Virginia between 1980 to 1992, Zeamer was actively involved in the lesbian-feminist movement. During this time, she opened a traveling lesbian book business called New Country Books. She also participated extensively in the production of women's music festivals, workshops, readings, and Take Back the Night Marches.
    Zeamer and her partner Sue Moorman live in Hatfield, MA. She has been a full-time realtor since retiring from federal service in 2008.
    - Video interview of Kathleen Zeamer, 2019-S-0016
    - Transcript of interview of Kathleen Zeamer, 2019 March 31; 2019-S-0016 (Box 2)